I want to show you how can you build
your own cursor for X a genic software
that can complete specific task in
certain vertical you're familiar with
one of the most interesting thing in
2025 is that vertical aenic software
going to be where the value going to
capture AI coding is the first agent use
case that hit a real part of market fit
and we saw some insane reu growth across
almost all AI coding tools but what I
believe is there will be so many
different vertical agents to be built
for the next 24 months and your capacity
was talking about cursor for slice
should exist but didn't. Then
immediately we start seeing people
building prototypes for this cursor for
slice part and there will also be cursor
for spreadsheets, cursor for design and
cursor for video editing. There will be
so many different vertical agents that
can be built that streamline the whole
end to end process and integrate deeply
for certain type of knowledge work. And
that's why today I want to show you how
can we actually build such cursor for X
a genic software. So how do you build a
cursor or a Jenga software? The most
common and adopt a pattern is that you
need to build agent that has access to
different tools and assistance to be
able to complete certain valuable
tasking and workflow. The example for
cursor is that it's able to write codes
create new file run command line and
even do get push search for the latest
dog stuff like that. So this is the
agent that you need to build and on the
other side you will need some sort of
specialized playground or canvas to help
users to review track progress of the
work that agent delivered as well as
co-working with agent. Again if I take
cursor as example this playground canva
is a code editor where users can see the
result comes through and jumping in to
make changes if they want and all the
context on the left side will be
automatically bring to the agent chat.
So agent will always have a context
about what a user is seeing here and
there are many examples from cursor wind
surf to Google stitchy which is UI
generation platform or even software
like clava which is building cursor for
video editing you still have this kind
of chat experience on the left side for
user to interact with AI but on the
right side you can design best UX for
user to review the result and I
personally believe there's just so many
opportunities to build cursor for X it
could be cursor for writing cursor for
video editing cursor for even planning a
PRD. That's why today I want to showcase
how do you build such cursor for X
system. But before we dive in, if you're
a soloreneur who are serious about
building AI startups fast and on budget,
there's an insanely good free resource
you need to check out called How to
Build an AI startup in three hours with
less than $500 by Greg Eisenberg. If you
don't know Greg Eisenberg, I've done a
podcast with him last year showcasing my
AI coding workflow and he always had ton
of great idea about what type of product
idea to build as solopreneur. In this
free resource, he walk us through a real
five-step framework using agents to
replace devs, marketers, PMs, literally
building a whole star solo with AI. He
talks through platforms and places where
he go to research and find the right
product idea to build as well as his
specific process of how to scope out the
MVP the minimum variable product so you
can bring your idea to market as fast as
possible using tools like manus lindy
and even cursor itself as well as his
secret source of how to do vibe
marketing. Everything in this PDF aligns
perfectly with what I'm going to show
you in ter of building this agent
software. So if you're a soloreneur who
are trying to build a product fast and
shipping smarter with AI agents,
definitely go and check out this free
resource. I have put a link in the
description below for you to get this
awesome resource for free. Now without
further ado, let's get into how to build
such cursor for X platform. So we're
going to build the whole agentic system
using Versel AI SDK. If you don't know
Versel AI SDK, it is open source package
created by Versel. They allow to build
aic software including backend, front
end in Typescript. There are a lot of
companies like Perplexity Vzero all
built based up pawn AI SDK. So it's
production ready and extremely simple to
set up. And if you're not familiar with
TypeScript also don't worry I'll take
you through step by step. So Versail AI
SDK has two main parts. One is core
which allow you to set up aic or large
learning model and UI which allow you to
stream results to the front end very
easily. With AI SDK core you can connect
to different large learning model
provider. Traditionally, each provider
has its own syntax. And with AISDK core,
you can swap out different models
without changing the underlying logic in
your codebase. So this will allow you to
experiment different models much easier
and they also provide you ways to build
agents connect to different tools and
MCPS as well. So this AI SDK core on the
other side, they also have AI SDK UI. It
will enable you to stream the results no
matter whether it's text structured
output like JSON or to call on the front
end in a very efficient way. So you can
build production level a genetic
applications. I'll cover both parts. In
the end you will be able to build a
cursor type of software is helping you
generate PRD and learning content.
Firstly let's cover the AI SDK core. So
vers SDK provide a few different
functions for generate text generate
object which is structure output as well
as tool code. So you can convert that to
into a agent very easily. To demonstrate
that I will open new folder in cursor
and do pmppm init to firstly set up a
typescript project. Then we're going to
install AI SDK. Just pmppm install AI.
This will add the versel AI SDK and I
can create a main.ts file. So to use
that I can do import entropic from AI
SDK and tropic. As we mentioned before
vers SDK allow you to call different
model provider. All you need to do just
install separate package for different
model provider. So if I'm using entropic
here I will open terminal and do pmppm
install at AI SDK/entropic.
But if you want to use open AI, you can
just change this to be open AAI instead
and import that from the package. Then I
can define the model entropic by passing
on the model name here. Next, I will
import generate text from AI package and
create a function answer question where
we're passing on the prompt and inside
this function, we just call this
generate text function and passing on
model and prompt. This will return
object that including text property
which is a string. So we're going to
return text and we can call this
function in the end. So that's pretty
much it. I will quickly create a Menv
file and add my entropic API key here
and in my TypeScript I will import this
EMV file and also do npm installv.
So now I can test run this script. I can
do ts node main.ts and when you run this
function you will see the result showing
here. If you haven't installed ts node
it is basically package that allow you
to compile your typescript file into
javascript and then run the javascript.
You can do pmppm at ts node typescript.
So this is how you can use AI SDK to
generate text. As I mentioned before,
they allow to do the streaming extremely
easy. So we can just change this
generate text to be stream text and
instead of using text, it will be a text
stream. Then we can do a for loop to
print out the result in console log. So
text stream will continue stream the
result back. If we run this, you can see
that it will actually return the stream
out the result. So you can reduce the
latency and provide much better UX. So
this is basically the AI SDK core. Very
simple. You can also pass a system
prompt here like you always return in
all caps and if we do it again it will
behave differently. Meanwhile, one
really cool thing is that it'll allow
you to do structured output but also
stream the structured output and this is
quite difficult to do with Python or I
wouldn't aware of very easy way to do
that Python but with Bristol AI SDK is
extremely easy. So I can change this to
be stream object. All we need to do is
just passing on a additional property
called schema. So if you're familiar
with Python you probably use uh like
pandantic but in Typescript you'll be
using zot. So open terminal and do pmppm
install zot zot is basically pandatic in
typescript. So I can do zobject title z
dot string and then passing on a
specific schema with title author data
and content. And you can also add
description as well. So the author I can
just add describe the author is always
JSON and if you're familiar with the
concept of structure output those
description as well as title here will
basically help agent to understand how
to generate those data and instead of
text string it will include one thing
called partial object string it's
basically partial JSON so if I run this
again it will return a JSON and stream
the result here. So this how you can
stream structure output but more than
that I will also show you how easy it is
to build an agent with AI SDK. I'm going
to change this to string text and we can
pass on tools as additional properties.
So our import tool from the AI SDK again
and we can define a tool called weather
by giving the description the parameters
which is input and the function it needs
to execute and our swap text to response
response including everything like the
message as well as two calls. So if I
run this you can see that it has message
here that assistant called the tool and
tool got executed as well. And what's
really cool about this is that you can
actually change this to be an agent by
passing on a property max steps. So if I
set a max step as 10 and run again, this
time it actually run a for loop where it
generate two call it call tools and
finally generate the final message. So
you actually don't need to build your
own agent runtime. All you need to do
just pass on this max steps. So this is
kind of fundamental of AI SDK core. If
you want to learn more in depth, I have
a whole section in AI builder club about
how to build production ready large
language model application where I will
take you through step by step in depth
of some advanced tips in terms of using
cell AI SDK to build such a generic
software effectively. I put a link in
the description below for you to join if
you're interested. Now I'll also show
you how to use AI SDK UI to quickly
build a web application with this chat
agent. So I'm going to open cursor again
and this time let's set up a nextJS
project. Uh I'm going to use chassen as
a UI library. So we can do mpm dlx
chassen as latest initial in it. I'll
choose next.js and name could be cursor
for x and you can choose any color and
I'll do cursor cursor for x. This will
open cursor in that specific folder. So
now you'll see that this nextjs app has
been set up. Your homepage will be in
this page.tsx.
So if we run pmppm devaf you can see
this page has been loaded which is
whatever displaying here. So now let's
say want to build such a system where
users can chat to the agent and agent
will be able to do some task present
result in the canva on the right side.
So structure is that on any web
application you have front end which is
one you see here that rendering the UI
for the user and back end which is
actual functionality. So we will set up
API endpoint first where it will use a
stream text to create that agent back
end which is similar to what we just
showed you earlier and then on the front
end I'm going to show you how do we use
AI SDK the UI part to get the results
from stream text and present on the
front end. So firstly we will need to
create a API endpoint and the normal
structure is that we'll create a API
folder and inside there we will create
another folder called chat and inside we
will create a route.ts ts our import
openai zod stream text data structure
return as we see earlier looks something
like this it have row content and also
two invocation so two invocation will be
showing the two call and it will have
different state so partial two call
means it is still generating the two
call inputs and the state call means it
finished the two call now it's actually
executing the function and result means
it actually get result back so you can
use this to display different sort of UI
for the function and here we just
created interface which is define the
data structure so you can use to
validate any function to and making sure
passing on the right data structure and
then let's say we want to give agent two
different tools one is get location
another is get a weather here I will
just create two mock function for
demonstration so we're define the
latitude and longitude then this is just
syntax in typescript for it to define
the type so it can automatically
validate if it is actually passing
number as latitude same for get weather
then we can define the actual endpoint
by doing function post so When we call
this API endpoint, we're probably
passing through message. This is syntax
in Typescript for you to get a specific
property from this JSON. This is same as
getting data and then getting specific
property within this data. Then we can
call this stream text passing on the
model system prompt message as well as
the tools which is similar to what we
just showed you earlier. And we'll
return result two data stream results.
Here I forgot to add the type check for
the message. So this is the API endpoint
for chat. Then we can go to your
homepage let's say and I'm going to
replace this uh firstly I will do use
client to indicate that this is a front
end client component because that
typescript at default is always server
side then I will do import use chat from
AI SDK react so this use chat is a
component that allow us to stream the
result by calling this use chat passing
on API which means it will send the
request to our chat API endpoint and set
max step to be five so it will be a for
loop autonomous agent that run max five
steps and we will get a few things back.
So message is actual message history
which it contain the data that we're
going to use to render on front end. So
input and set input is a state that use
chat return to indicate what type of
value is inside the chat input now and a
pen will basically send a new message to
the agent. Then we can write a front end
here where it has input the value is the
input of this chat and every time when
the input change it will set input here
and if a user do enter then we will
trigger the agent and passing on the
latest message and in the end this
message map will show all the message
from the agent. So now let's try to run
this by open terminal and do pmppm dev.
And now if I open terminal so UI here
you can't see anything but you will see
that this input on the top left corner
and if I do hi you can see that the
result has been showing here and prompt
check my weather it will call to and
return me the result. So this example of
how to build a chat interface and
obviously the interface looks really bad
but this is kind of easy part. We can
also render the two call better as well.
So this quick version ask cursor to do
if the message has two invocations then
we'll display those two invocations
inside this two invocation render. So
each two invocation will have two name
two call ID state arguments which is
input as well as result. So if the state
is partial call or call then we will
show it loading state the two name as
well as the inputs. But if it's already
completed then we will show the inputs
as well as a read off. And now you get
this pretty good chat agent experience
where it can talk to you and complete
actions return results. But those are
just some more simple functionality.
Quite often you want your agent to call
another sub aent or using a tool that is
actually calling large language model
that can take a while for it to run. In
this type of experience you actually
want it to stream the results back to
the front end while the tool is running.
And how can you do that? Versel AI SDK
natively doesn't support that. You do
need to update a little bit and here is
how you can do it. So I can create a
function here called generate prd that
is calling another large language model.
So if the agent just call this tool this
stream text is not going anywhere and
what do you need is this create data
stream response function from versel AI
SDK. This allow to merge multiple
different stream together and push
custom data to front end. So for this
endpoint instead of calling the stream
text directly we're going to return this
create data stream response and inside
this function we will have this execute
function. it will have this data stream
writer that allow to send more data. But
let's say we have this tool called
generate PRD inside this generate PRD
execution. I'll call the generate PRD
function that we defined earlier which
should return the stream text object.
Then I will have this for loop for each
chunk from the PDF stream. We'll do PDF
stream for string. This will return all
the stream events and for each chunk
from the streaming if the stream type
equal to text delta which means it's
getting new text then we will do this
data stream writer.r write data send a
new text delta into the data stream and
this will basically send new text data
as we go but I would suggest you add
more metadata here so you will know what
this data is about and then we'll join
all the text chunk together so we get
the final prd content and in the end
we'll do result merge into data stream
with this data stream writer so result
is the original stream text of our
parent agent and merge into data stream
will connect two data stream together so
with this one You can basically send any
source of data back to the front end.
But those data won't be showing as part
of message. You need to get a new
property from result called data. This
will contain those custom data that send
from the endpoint. So in our case, I can
create a new function called PRD
display. So here we will filter out all
the data with this type PRD content and
then we'll group all the content based
on different tool call ID and in the end
join all the chunk of data together and
display the full content and there are
some logics to render it on the front
end as well. So here is a quick demo. If
I give a task generate PRD for to-do app
it recording this tool but here is a
mock I put in here that will stream the
results of the nest to call. So this
example of how can you stream the two
core response back to the front end. So
got agent part working well and stream
the data. Next we need to build a
playground or canvas to create a space
for user to review the results from the
agent and co-working with agent. So to
implement the playground on the right
side we need to create a UI component
for the playground. And in our case we
can build a simple text editor for
helping people build PRD. But apart from
the UI itself, we also need a way for
agent chat to communicate data back to
the playground. So that when agent try
to generate like a PRD doc, it can
safely generate data into database. So
next time we open the page, it's already
showing up in the playground. But apart
from long-term persistent database, we
also need something called state. So
state is almost some sort of short-term
memory that share across different
components or within a component. For
example, now we probably have a state
called current PRD doc as well as set
current PRD doc. Those states can be
shared across those components. And why
do we need state is because it's much
faster since we want to stream out the
result as we go. But meanwhile, we are
also going to store that into probably a
PRD doc in the database as well as a
conversation message. And to implement
this just to keep the application more
maintainable, putting all the logic into
one page.tsx file, we will first
restructure this page into different
components. I have a project page that
has this kind of split panel layout and
I will turn our current chat UI into
this chat panel and the content panel to
the right side and then we'll implement
a state to share across this two panels
and in the end we'll connect to
superbase to set up a back end. So for
this UI restructure I think the
requirement is pretty clear already.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to ask
cursor to do it. So I'll give a prompt.
Now let's do a UI restructure. I want to
create a project/p project id page. So
this is just syntax in next.js JS means
the URL will look something like perjury
id and inside project id page it has
split view left side is chat right side
is content panel showing the prd doc
generated and create a chat paneltsx
component and create content panel
component and in the end create a state
that is shared between chat panel and
content panel so we can stream a data
result to content panel I will trigger
that okay now we have this new
application UI that has two different
components left chat and right size
documents and this one folder per id has
been created and here we have a shared
state called per data so state you can
consider as a short-term database or
short-term memory every time the state
chain it will trigger the UI to be
rerendered and normally comes in pair it
will define the state data and a
function to set a state data so here we
define this project data with a set
function to set a message data and it's
loading then we'll pass this set data to
chat panel so that when chat panel
receive those additional streaming data
from the API endpoint. It can set the
project data which we'll be using to
render on the content panel. And now if
we go inside the chat panel, it will
have those functions still to render the
tool response message and the actual
chat panel function will receive project
ID and set project data function. And we
will do this use effect. So use event
you can consider uh as a kind of event
listener. It will always monitor those
data that you put in here. So every time
when message lens change or data lens
change or is loading state change it
will trigger list of function you define
here. So here we're basically saying
every time a message or data changed
then let's set a project data again and
the rest is kind of similar to what we
have before and inside the content panel
we'll create this prd display is join
all the chunk of prd dog into one and
display on this content panel. So now we
have a split view. I can ask it to
generate prd for me for a to-do app.
Then on the right side it will be start
streaming the data. I can view those
content. It will automatically generate
V1 V2 based on time stamp. So if I ask
it to generate again with some charts.
Now it will switch to V2 and show me the
list of data here. So this how you can
create a genic system that has both chat
experience and playground using Versel
AI. If you want to learn more, there's a
one section in the AI builder club
called build production launch language
model applications. And there's one
section I just added for Versel AI SDK
that has detailed step-by-step breakdown
of how to build a system that I just
showcase you. And I will also attach a
GitHub repo there as well. I'll cover in
a different video about how to connect
this to superbase back end and set up a
user OS and usage based pricing tier. So
if you're interested, you can click on
the link in the description below to
join AI builder club where we're going
to have a 30 days challenge for you to
build a cursor for X application. And
for every week during the months, I will
take you through specific parts of how
to build such system. Meanwhile, I also
made a new version of SAS launch kit
that already have the authentication and
usage based drive haven built-in. So you
can focus on just building the agent
itself. I hope you enjoyed this video.
If you want to see more of this type of
content, please comment below. Thank you
and I see you next time.